<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>mathematics on Zach Beever</title>
    <link>https://zbeever.github.io/tags/mathematics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in mathematics on Zach Beever</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2020 09:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://zbeever.github.io/tags/mathematics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Some proofs in elementary linear algebra</title>
      <link>https://zbeever.github.io/post/2020-09-10_elementary-linear-algebra/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2020 09:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://zbeever.github.io/post/2020-09-10_elementary-linear-algebra/</guid>
      <description>This semester, a controls class I&amp;rsquo;m enrolled in has promised to be proof-based. Writing proofs is not a muscle I exercise often, so I figured it would be best to get back into things with some proofs of elementary theorems in linear algebra. This is not going to be a particularly exciting post&amp;mdash;it&amp;rsquo;s mainly done for the benefit of myself.
Prerequisites: To understand this post, you should be familiar with linear algebra.
Recommended Reading: Linear Algebra Done Right by Sheldon Axler. Finite Dimensional Linear Systems by Roger Brockett.
Linear dependence and span Theorem: Given a vector space \(V\) over a field \(\mathbb{F}\) and a spanning set \(V_0 = \lbrace v_1, \dots, v_n\rbrace\) with \(v_i \in V\) for \(i = 1,\dots,n\), an arbitrary linearly indepdendent set of vectors \(U = \lbrace u_1, \dots, u_k\rbrace\) with \(u_j\in V\) for \(j=1,\dots,k\) has at most \(n\) elements.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The prisoner problem (no, not that one)</title>
      <link>https://zbeever.github.io/post/2020-08-16_prisoner-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2020 05:15:31 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://zbeever.github.io/post/2020-08-16_prisoner-problem/</guid>
      <description>During her Master&amp;rsquo;s program, my girlfriend signed up for a Putnam Competition preparation course. She doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a background in math, but she thought it would be fun&amp;mdash;and it was! There were lots of interesting practice problems we solved together and this was my favorite.
Prerequisites: To understand this post, you should have some knowledge of modular arithmetic.
Recommended Reading: The Putnam Competition website.
The setup Imagine a room with \(N\) prisoners. They are going to play a game for their freedom. They can talk amongst themselves and come up with a strategy before the game starts, but as soon as it begins they are immobile and unable to communicate.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>