<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Zach Beever</title>
    <link>https://zbeever.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Zach Beever</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Aug 2020 15:03:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://zbeever.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The geometry of mechanics</title>
      <link>https://zbeever.github.io/post/2020-08-18_geometry-of-mechanics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Aug 2020 15:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://zbeever.github.io/post/2020-08-18_geometry-of-mechanics/</guid>
      <description>If you&amp;rsquo;ve spent time with analytical mechanics, you&amp;rsquo;ve probably stumbled upon the concept of a symplectic manifold. In particular, you&amp;rsquo;ve probably heard how Hamiltonian mechanics is naturally described by a symplectic manifold. Unfortunately, many sources explaining why this is so are opaque to the uninitiated or painfully slow to get to the point. I&amp;rsquo;ll try to outline the geometric picture of mechanics using a combination of qualitative and quantitative arguments. This borrows quite a bit from Henry Cohn&amp;rsquo;s note on the topic, so I recommend you check it out.
Prerequisites: To understand this post, you should be comfortable with differential geometry and its two most popular notations: indicial notation and coordinate-free notation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The prisoner problem (no, not that one)</title>
      <link>https://zbeever.github.io/post/2020-08-16_prisoner-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2020 05:15:31 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://zbeever.github.io/post/2020-08-16_prisoner-problem/</guid>
      <description>During her Master&amp;rsquo;s program, my girlfriend signed up for a Putnam Competition preparation course. She doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a background in math, but she thought it would be fun&amp;mdash;and it was! There were lots of interesting practice problems we solved together and this was my favorite.
Prerequisites: To understand this post, you should have some knowledge of modular arithmetic.
Recommended Reading: The Putnam Competition website.
The setup Imagine a room with \(N\) prisoners. They are going to play a game for their freedom. They can talk amongst themselves and come up with a strategy before the game starts, but as soon as it begins they are immobile and unable to communicate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The evolving Harris current sheet model</title>
      <link>https://zbeever.github.io/post/2020-08-15_harris-current-sheet/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 12:57:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://zbeever.github.io/post/2020-08-15_harris-current-sheet/</guid>
      <description>In many space physics papers investigating nonadiabatic current sheet scattering, the simplified Harris model is used. In Cartesian coordinates, it takes on the form
$$\mathbf{B} = B_x\tanh\Big(\frac{z}{L}\Big)\hat{\mathbf{i}} + 0\hat{\mathbf{j}} + B_z\hat{\mathbf{k}}$$
where \(L\) parameterizes the current sheet thickness. This is nice approximation for a relatively static magnetosphere, but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t capture a thinning current sheet. For that, we&amp;rsquo;ll need to make the change \(L=L(t)\). In turn, this will induce an electric field. What is the expression for that field?
Prerequisites: To understand this post you&amp;rsquo;ll need to be familiar with Maxwell&amp;rsquo;s equations. To understand the motivation of this post, familiarity with basic space plasma physics and the structure of the magnetosphere is necessary.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A derivation of the Leibniz isochronous curve</title>
      <link>https://zbeever.github.io/post/2020-08-15_leibniz-isochronous-curve/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 12:43:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://zbeever.github.io/post/2020-08-15_leibniz-isochronous-curve/</guid>
      <description>Recently, a friend of mine shared with me the idea of the Leibniz isochronous curve. In words, this is the trajectory a frictionless object would follow if its vertical velocity was left unchanged by a constant, downward force. Using the standard \(x\)-\(y\) Cartesian axes, the curve is parameterized by
$$\begin{aligned}x &amp;amp;= x(t)\\y &amp;amp;= -v_0t\end{aligned}$$
where \(v_0\) is positive. What is the exact expression for \(x(t)\)?
Prerequisites: To understand this post you&amp;rsquo;ll need to be comfortable with the Lagrangian formulation of classical mechanics.
Recommended Reading: The Variational Principles of Mechanics by Cornelius Lanczos. The Theoretical Minimum by George Hrabovsky and Leonard Susskind.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>